A Guide to the Atcheson L. Hench Autograph Collection
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series II: Collection of Modern Autographs
  - 1867 August 11 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to Hurd & Houghton, writes that he has seen both of their kind notes and will look for the Charles Dickens books to arrive for his review, 1 page, with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 8:59)
  - 1867 August 20 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to [Hurd & Houghton], encloses his notices about "London Society" and "The Riverside" from his paper The Richmond Southern Opinion, 1 page, with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 8:59)
  - 1880 March 11 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to Hurd & Houghton, requests a copy of Dealings with the Dead advertised by their company and also a few months of [Boston Evening Transcript?] in exchange for a letter about Southern affairs, 1 page, with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 8:59)
  - 1872 November 7 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to "Gentlemen" [J.R. Osgood and Company], asks for a selection of their recent publications that they would like noticed in the South, offering to promote their company by "extensively advertising, in careful reviews the names, subjects, and literary characteristics of your books as they appear." He particularly mentions The Pennsylvania Pilgrim, and Other Poems by John Greenleaf Whittier (1807-1892) and The Life of Abraham Lincoln by Ward Hill Lamon (1828-1893), 2 pages on 1 l., with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 8:60)
  - 1882 April 9 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to William H. Rideing, explains his neglect in answering his letter due to illness and hopes that Rideing will receive from [Alexander Hamilton] Stephens "many valuable reminiscences drawn from his long varied and peculiar experiences" for The Youth's Companion; and says of Stephens "Not only is Stephens a statesman (in contradiction from that very clever but commonplace thing known as the mere politician) but he is likewise pre-eminently a gentleman.", 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 8:61)
  - 1867 September 26 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to "Gentlemen" [Roberts Brothers, Boston?], encloses two reviews of recent works, "one a somewhat elaborate critique of The Book of the Sonnet, [edited by Leigh Hunt and Samuel Adams Lee] another, of Miss [Jean] Ingelow's last work"; also asks for a copy of The Life and Death of Jason, A Poem by William Morris (1834-1896) to review; and calls the review of Miss Jean Ingelow's A Story of Doom and Other Poems in The Atlantic absurd., 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 8:62)
  - 1884 July 26 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to Clinton Scollard (1860-1932), asks for a manuscript copy of the sonnet that Scollard has written about Hayne as described by Mr. Butterworth, 1 page with envelope, with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 8:63)
  - 1884 August 22 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to Clinton Scollard (1860-1932), thanks him for the copy of his sonnet, of which he says "It is a very true and admirable work of art & whether I deserve its commendation, or not, there can be no doubt of the poetical merit of your performance." 1 page, with envelope, with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 8:63)
  - 1868 January Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to the Editor of Southern Society, suggests that his paper should not only discuss contemporary questions but that they should also entertain varied themes, with "legends, facts, histories, biographical sketches, etc. from the past." Hayne has also sent in a package with a review of "Opportunity" and two papers for the editorial column. 1 page, with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 8:64)
  - 1882 February 10 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to [Alexander Hamilton?] Stephens (1812-1883), introduces Stephens to William H. Rideing, attached to the Western Geographical Surveys under Lt. Wheeler in 1875-1876, and currently associated with the firms of Harpers & Scribner, New York, and "author of several brilliant works of which A Saddle in the Wild West is especially noteworthy for its rich humor, picturesque descriptions, and valuable practical information as to the People & Climate of New Mexico, Arizona, Nevada, Eastern California, etc.", 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:65)
  - 1867 October 23 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to "My Dear Stoddard," expresses his heartfelt thanks for Stoddard's beautiful volume of poems and encloses his review of the book from the Richmond Southern Opinion mentioning that he is "sick & oppressed by many troubles.", 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:66)
  - 1877 December 24 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to Charles Warren Stoddard (1843-1909) while discussing his own work, Hayne informs Stoddard that the poems that he likes the most in his book The Mountain of Lovers are the ones about nature and that "the chief narrative piece was composed in a very unlucky vein; and I bitterly regret its publication. Indeed my Legends & Lyrics issued by Lippincott in 1972 contain the only two narrative poems I really value." He goes on to express his concern for his friend's depression and despondency and writes at length with advice to take care of his physical health, to avoid or forego the use of stimulants, and to engage in some engrossing physical work. He also asks for him to send South Sea Idylls and not to worry about its condemnation in England, "I recollect Byron's saying (true for once) that the English are often seized by periodical fits of a squeamish morality." Hayne wants to know Stoddard's opinion of his poem "Unveiled" published in Scribner's about which he says, "Swinburne also wrote me very kindly and enthusiastically about that poem.", 6 pages on 2 l. (6435) (Box-folder 8:67)
  - 1867 April 13 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to "My Dear Sir," writes that he has enjoyed his contributions to both The Californian and Galaxy Magazine and asks if his editor pays for contributions because "relying on the pen for support, since the War utterly ruined me, I can't write for absolutely nothing: but my charges are reasonable I think.", 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 8:68)
  - 1867 November 5 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to "Dear Sir," having thought his paper one of the most brilliant of the last few months sent to him for his column on "Reminiscences and Anecdotes of the War" in The Southern Opinion and asks for some other contribution from the pen of the writer., 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:69)
  - 1873 January 10 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to "My Dear Madam," informs her that Messrs. E.J. Hale & Son have just published The Poems of Henry Timrod, with a sketch of the poet's life, by Paul H. Hayne, which he has requested be sent to her. He also asks that she continue to send him a copy of her Bazaar free since "I had your "prospectus published and more than that, I shall (as usual) allude to your weekly & its excellencies from time to time, & thus do you 'yeoman's service' with the Southern public." 2 pages on 1 l., with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 8:70)
  - 1875 March 24 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to "My Dear Friend," expresses deep concern over reports about his health as reported in a Northern paper, 1 page, with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 8:71)
  - 1875 April 18 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to "Dear Sir," having sent him an autograph in September 1874, Hayne now writes hoping he will be interested in his new volume of poetry The Mountain of the Lovers, with Poems of Nature & Tradition enough to write a paragraph or two about his book for some prominent journals, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 8:72)
  - 1877 December 5 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to "My Dear Madam," accepts her offer of ten dollars for his lyric, "Motes" and says of her magazine Wide Awake "it is simple justice to say, that a prettier, neater, more entertaining juvenile periodical, has never made its appearance in the U.S." Ella Farman Pratt (1837-1907) was one of the editors of Wide Awake. 2 pages on 1 l., with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 8:73)
  - 1879 April 5 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to "Dear Sir," sends the last two volumes of his poems, supposedly for a translation into German by his correspondent, 1 page, with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 8:74)
  - 1880 September 1 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to "Dear Sir," believes there must be a mistake about his receipt of American Lyrics from the publisher since he never ordered the work except as an exchange for his own poems. He also mentions Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, "while in Boston last season I saw my old friend Mr. Longfellow, and delivered to him the message you sent through me, when I was in the W[hite] Mountains, N[ew] H[amphire] - but I did not meet Mr. Arthur Gilman, altho since then I have heard from him in reference to some of my verses for his Collection." 1 page, with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 8:75)
  - 1883 February 21 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to "Dear Sir," sends this note in reply to an autograph request, 1 page, with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 8:76)
  - 1883 February 27 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to "My Dear Sir," expresses his opinion about the writer's prize essay on George Eliot, "It is admirably conceived & [carefully] executed. Not only have you seized in my judgment upon the salient points of her genius & productions, but these are represented clearly and forcibly in a style of unusual terseness and vigor.", 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:77)
  - 1883 May 12 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to "My Dear Sir," sends his autograph with pleasure and is thankful that his poems have benefitted his reader both as influence for good and intellectually, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 8:78)
  - 1884 March 8 Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) to "Gentlemen," Boston Office, sends a notice of Mr. Hazard's recent work and asks that more books be sent to him to review, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:79)
  - n.d. Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) Engraving, engraved for The Eclectic by J.J. Ade, New York (6435) (Box-folder 8:80)
  - 1877-1885, n.d. Paul Hamilton Hayne (1830-1886) Poetry, including a line from "Thunder at Midnight," "The Ultimate Faith," "Quatrain," and "Ma Belle", 5 items (6435) (Box-folder 8:81)
  - 1894 Jan23 William Hamilton Hayne (1856-1929) to Walter R. Benjamin (1854- ), autograph dealer, Hayne arranges to purchase the Pinckney letter concerning the appointment of his grandfather, Paul Hamilton Hayne, as a midshipman., 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 8:82)
  - 1879 August 7 William Hamilton Hayne (1856-1929) to William F. Gable, in his father's absence, he sends two brief poems and a couple of signatures from a pile of manuscripts; he also suggests that Gable can secure a photograph of his father from Messrs. Pelot and Cole, Augusta, Georgia; they have made the latest and best photograph of Paul Hamilton Hayne which was used for the steel portrait in [William Cullen] Bryant's Library of Poetry and Song, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:83)
  - 1886 December 13 William Hamilton Hayne (1856-1929) to Clinton Scollard (1860-1932), thanks him for the poetical tribute to his father; both his mother and Hayne think highly of the poem "Threnody" and he goes on to praise his books of poetry Pictures in Song, With Reed and Lyre; he also expresses his appreciation of their mutual acquaintance, Samuel Minturn Peck (1854-1914), who did a review of With Reed and Lyre in The Southern Bivouac, 4 pages on 1 l., with typed transcript (6435) (Box-folder 8:84)
  - 1827 June 6 [Felicia Dorothea (Browne) Hemans] (1793-1835) to Mary Russell Mitford (1787-1855) shares her deep appreciation for Our Village and requests an autograph for a friend of hers, [John Luxmore], the Bishop of St. Asaph, 1815-1830, 3 pages on 1 l., signature has been cut out (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:85)
  - 1895 February 25 William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to "My dear Pawling" [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922), a business partner in the publishing firm of William Heinemann, Henley writes that Walter Blaikie visited yesterday morning and "all manner of thanks for Max Nordau & Pugh. The letter I've yet to tackle. What I've read of the other is vastly amusing & - as I think - only untrue because it's overstated. However, we'll talk of him anon. Meanwhile, I think he should succeed." Henley also expresses gratitude that Pawling likes the last number of [The New Review?], Henley edited The New Review from 1895-1897; asks him to send The Realm and the North American Review if he has them; and mentions [J.W.] Gilmer, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:86)
  - 1895 October 23 William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922), writes that he has not seen either the caricature or report and asks that they be sent to him; and notes that his wife would like a score of copies so printed of an unknown article or print, 1 page (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:87)
  - 1895 December 24 William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922), encloses two more "Wyndhamisms [George Wyndham?]; one about your proposal, and one about an idea of his own." He also had no luck with Ernest and Coleridge and mentions other possibilities for The New Review that he has in mind. He also discusses his desire to publish some unpublished Burns letters in a volume and the copyright issue. Henley writes in a postscript "Coleridge writes, by the way: -'A Torquay bookseller - King, Union Street - had last summer a volume of printed but unpublished Byron correspondence, price 5/5 pounds. I don't know if it is worth asking about.' I think it is. What say you?, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:87)
  - 1896 July 30 William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922), discusses his negotiations with a bank for a loan and mentions his Byron project and the need to talk to W.H. [William Heinemann?] about it, 2 page on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:88)
  - 1897 November 22 William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922), thanks his correspondent for the news of the death of an elderly unnamed common friend, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:89)
  - [ca.1898 March] William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922), appreciates that Whittier liked his work and mentions the death of T.E.B. [Thomas Edward Brown], "I've written a quatorzain for our last N.R. [New Review] on my dear and never to be forgotten T.E.B. It's not what I meant it to be; but I dare say you'll understand and forgive.", 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:90)
  - 1898 April 5 William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922), thanks him for the fifty and writes concerning his brother, Ted [Edward John Henley], "I hope with all my soul that [Hurd?] will fall into line. (a) for the Journal's sake & (b) for Ted's. He needs work & he needs money." He also writes "I understand from Percy H. that the Journal closed this morning. But I'll write of it next week without fail. I thought the thing out this afternoon & I find I've lots of good to say.", 1 page (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:91)
  - 1900 January 17 William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922), informs him that [William?] Nicholson has not written; tries to arrange a time for Pawling to visit suggesting Sunday and mentions his prior commitments, including a long day with C.W. [Charles Whibley?] (over Rabelais), a musician, and Gilbert Parker on Saturday, both sides of a note card (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:92)
  - [ca. 1900] May William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922), blesses him for his "tater-patch, & your arbor, & your kidney-beans!" and the lending of the miniature of "an Immortal. I propose to build a special altar for it, & to burn leaves from Boxiana ... before it daily, as long as the book holds out." Henley writes that he is not in the frame of mind to write, with only two lyrics written in May, and it was good to have Nicholson visit, both sides of a note card (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:93)
  - 1901 February 18 William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922), wishes he could see Sydney again, having done all he can do to attract his sympathy; mentions Billy and his book, asking who is going to edit it; believes that [William?] Nicholson has done nobly with his illustrations, and rues his bad luck, "I would that blamed P.M.M. [Pall Mall Magazine?] had not fallen from me - that's all - I say no more.", 2 pages (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:94)
  - 1901 August 26 William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922), rejoices that his book of verses [Hawthorn and Lavender with Other Verses ?] is out of his hands at last and is pleased to dedicate it to one S.S.P. [Sydney Southgate Pawling] and is busy helping another author with his manuscript, "it is a curious work. Very interesting; not well-written; very long. But I think it will do.", 1 page (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:94)
  - 1901 September 6 William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922) offers up harsh criticism of an unnamed book, possibly by [William Nicholson], 1 page (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:94)
  - 1901 September 17 William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922), asks "What price Nicholson? Has he turned up the wood cut? And, if so, why? And how's he going to satisfy subscribers?" Also, asks if he knows anyone with a small, convenient flat to let for a month or to "loan it to an undistinguished man of letters for October." Both sides of a note card (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:94)
  - 1902 November 11 William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922), gives him a reference in Martin Chuzzlewit by Charles Dickens to check and asks him to visit, 1 page (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:95)
  - [ca. 1902] William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922), has made so many corrections and additions to the copy of the Complete Works of Henry Fielding typed by Miss W. That it would be impossible to send it in its present form to Croscup & Sterling Co., 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:96)
  - 1903 January 9 William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922), has asked Harper & Bros. to communicate with Mr. W.H. and notes that on the 22nd they will celebrate their Silver Wedding Day, 1 page (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:97)
  - 1903 January 19 William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922), asks him and Mrs. S.S. to turn up for his anniversary celebration, 1 page (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:97)
  - 1903 January 27 William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922), plans on keeping the manuscript a little while longer for proofing and asks for the Dictionary of National Biography entry for Christopher Graves, 1 page (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:97)
  - 1903 February 18 William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922), promises to send the manuscript on Tuesday morning after making a clean copy for him, 1 page (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:98)
  - 1903 March 20 William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922), discusses his payments for different pieces of work and asks for him to sneak one of the prints taken of himself by a photographer for Croscup & Sterling Co., 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:99)
  - 1903 May 5 William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922), fears they will miss the American copyright in book form, and Harpers & Bros. have not answered Nate's letter, 1 page (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:99)
  - n.d. William Ernest Henley (1849-1903) to [Sydney Southgate Pawling] (?-1922), encloses an item from David [Hannay?], and suggests that Hannay might do a reprint and editing of Robert Southey's Life of Nelson; and informs him, I add some scrabble about the Byron. I don't know if it will do. Let me see a proof, in any case, with your improvements & suggestions. Any portrait will do. Send Gilmer down for me. I've [heaps?] in the selection of 1 vol. B.s you sent.", 2 pages on 1 l. (6435-a) (Box-folder 8:100)
  - 1855 August 7 Henn, Williams & Co., Bankers, Dealers in Exchange and Lands, Fairfield, Iowa, to Herndon Frazer, Twyman's Store, Spotsylvania County, Virginia, answers Frazer's inquiry about lands in Winneshiek County, Iowa, in the extreme northern part of the state, 2 pages on 1 l., with envelope (6435) (Box-folder 8:101)
  - 1856 January 4 Joseph Henry (1797-1878), Secretary of the Smithsonian Institution, to Professor William Barton Rogers (1804-1882), requests copies of his lectures on the phases of the atmosphere delivered before the Smithsonian Institution to be published in an appendix, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:102)
  - 1884 January 12 Thomas Wentworth Higginson (1823-1911) to Miss Churchill, suggests that Mr. William Lee of Lee & Shepard might be able to answer her questions about the cost of publishing, 2 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 8:103)
  - 1906 August 16 Thomas Wentworth Higginson (1823-1911) to Messrs. Clarke & Co., tells them he can supply them with copies of the "little English printed book about me, translated from the French sketch by [?] Blanc" from the New York publisher from whom he purchased twenty copies, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:104)
  - 1907 February 4 Thomas Wentworth Higginson (1823-1911) to "My dear Cocke," asks if he can give him the address of "the agent of some organization in New York to aid in the organization of societies on socialism in colleges,", 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:105)
  - 1852 October 26 Thomas Wentworth Higginson (1823-1911) to A. Crosby, approves of the arrangements he and Mr. Spaulding have made for him to speak, plans to lecture at several lyceums next winter in the northern part of Essex County so hopes to be able to visit Newburyport, Massachusetts, when the prizes are awarded; mentions the benefit of the Ewing Schools, and their expansion, especially the ones at Portsmouth, Saco, and Dover, and mentions a Mr. Cutler in relation to the Ewing Schools, 3 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 8:106)
  - 1884 August 14 Thomas Wentworth Higginson (1823-1911) to Mr. Mead, thanks him for the pamphlet about the Presidential candidate, James G. Blaine, "which I carefully read but without conviction." Higginson believes a better case could be make for General [Butler?], "certainly as abler man than Blaine with more experience & more magnetism." He feels reasonably sure of Grover Cleveland's election, "You see I had more 'loyalty' than you credited me with in regard to Cleveland's nomination, and it may be the same as to his election, of which I feel reasonably confident.", 3 pages on 1 l. (6435) (Box-folder 8:107)
  - 1898 March 4 Thomas Wentworth Higginson (1823-1911) to Professor Parker, will come to the breakfast if he feels in good condition after speaking before the Folk Lore Association the night before, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:108)
  - 1896 May 11 Thomas Wentworth Higginson (1823-1911) to Mr. Putnam, sends a photograph of the best [Higginson?] family tree by Oswald Haldane, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:109)
  - 1896 June 28 Thomas Wentworth Higginson (1823-1911) to Mr. Putnam, encloses check upon receipt of his letter, 1 page (6435) (Box-folder 8:109)